Okay, so this is the first module in the long transcriptomic CFDE learning platform.
So I wanted to start off by introducing the CFDE main website, specifically looking at the CFDE workbench
and some of the different tools that they have available as we explore in this program two different ways to obtain the data.
Additionally, although there's not a screencast related to the module, there's an associated module zero
that helps guide you through with environmental setup and a little bit of
Python background if that is helpful for you. So to start off the CFD website
offers a couple different resources and primarily the ones that I'd like to
show you right now are, so if you go to this analyze tab you can see that there
is a subtab tools and workflows. If you click on that then you're going to be
able to see a list of different tools and workflows.
You can see this protein knowledge network
is a very interesting tool that I
like how they have it organized.
So you can use-- you can navigate to this page,
and you can see some additional resources that
will be most helpful for your enrichment strategy,
or if it was some sort of entity recognition work.
You have these external databases
that are going to help you identify genes and proteins
and pathways, biological processes, et cetera.
So that's relevant.
For this specific learning platform,
we're going to use MCIG-DP as well as Reactome primarily
and Gene Ontology.
So next, if we go back to the main CFD page,
there's also the opportunity to chat
with a virtual assistant.
So if we chat with the virtual assistant,
for this specific learning platform,
I wanted to introduce, hey, I'm interested in looking
at lung tissue, and more specifically,
I want to see what available resources CFD has
for single cell RNA-seq analyses,
as well as bulk RNA related to lung tissue.
So I query it, and I'm able to get the return response
related to HubMap being one primary identified resource,
And for the single cell and then for the bulk,
I see that GTX is also identified as a primary source.
So that's the use of this function,
this LLM can render some different results
depending on what your specific query is
and it's constantly being refined right now.
So just be patient if you don't get exactly
the same response that I have.
However, that is a useful tool to be able
to identify some of those databases.
In addition, so if you go to the Explore the Ecosystem,
you can go to the Data Matrix,
and you'll find yourself on this page here.
So now you have the CFDE interaction with these DCCs,
which are partner resources.
So then you can click directly on HubMap,
and it'll bring you to that specific website
for that data, as well as GTAC.
So now we'll go to HubMap,
and then navigate to the data portal
and you can go to data sets.
And then you can filter through as you see most needed.
For me specifically, if I wanted to find the lung tissue
I would select lung as well as looking at,
I wanted to focus on RNA-seq
so I can look at the different single cell RNA-seq.
So I will, however, just copy and paste one of the processed IDs
for each donor.
And then you'll be able to see that the data set populates.
And then you can scroll down to the data section.
And you can go to the file browser.
And you're going to want to source raw expression.
And that's going to be the primary data set
that you're going to require for this project.
And then in addition, if you wanted
to download what is needed, the metadata specifically
as well, you can go to this metadata section
and hit Download.
And it will download the metadata for you.
So real quickly, I will just go back to the module PDF,
which will be shared.
And you can see that we're using four donors here.
So donors one, two, three, and four.
And each respective ID is shared with you
so that you know what specific data sets you need to download.
In addition, so for the true multi-home integration
in module three, you will need this additional data set ID.
It's related to donor two.
And it exactly matches a taxic data with the single cell RNA
seek data.
So you can go back to the data search, and then type in that
ID, and then you'll see, again, it will bring you to that
specific data page.
and then you can download the multi-ohm MOFA HD F5 file
is what you're going to need.
So that is how you're going to source the necessary data
from HubMap.
And then similarly for GTX, you're
going to go to the main website.
You can go to Download and then Open Access Data.
You want bulk tissue expression,
and then you will scroll down to V10,
which is what we're using here.
And you can sort by tissue,
so then you can look and find lung,
so then you would find lung,
and then you could just download.
So you'll need both the reads as well as the TPMs.
And that is what you'll require from GTX,
And then, in addition, some external data resources
that we're going to integrate into this learning platform
will be both GEO and then NASA's open source data
repository, OSDR.
So the GEO data set that we'll integrate
is going to be related to idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis
so that we can look at aging effects
in a cross data comparison to some correlated gene expression
values in idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis.
And then similarly, to download this,
the appropriate data for this section,
you'll just need the actual count files right here,
and then as well as the series matrix files right here.
So that's going to be what you need.
And again, that'll be integrated into module four.
And then also for module four, we're
going to integrate a space study as we look at NASA OSTR data
related to OSD 248, where we had lung tissue that
was sampled from rodent research programs that
flew aboard the ISS.
So here, you will go down into the file section,
and then you can see the different tabs,
but all of the specific file names and everything
are going to be located in module one as well.
So you can specifically refer to that additional document
and then download the necessary files.
The specifically here though, you will want
the RNA sequence differential expression,
R-N-A-R-M-G-L-Ball-Garneseek, this file,
as well as the metadata.
And you will also want the sample tables,
and you will want the,
you want the unnormalized counts,
So that is, yeah, you want the unnormalized R SEM,
unnormalized counts, R NAR, GL bulk.
So again, the complete list of the files
that you're going to use are located in the PDF
that we'll now transition to.
So this is module one is really the entry point
for this long transcriptomics course.
covers that require datasets as we kind of just went over and then how to copy them,
whether you use the web interface or you do it programmatically, it'll walk you through each.
So it kind of goes through what specific prerequisites are needed. It identifies the
different donors that we're going to use. It outlines the directory layout in addition. So the
directory that you'll download will have the IDs associated with each individual donor. So
So you can always obtain the specific IDs that way.
And then there's two different options.
The minimum download is going to be really preferred,
where it amounts to 814.87 megabytes.
And this is all that is needed to run the program end to end.
So I would highly recommend this.
If you wanted to explore some different options,
you could look at the second option, which
the full download which extends up to 65 gigabytes and then you can kind of extend for the secondary
analyses from HubMap as well as you know some additional NAS OSDR studies OSD 464 could also
be included into that pipeline but again I would just start with option one probably as
as the your primary route. So you'll go through you'll obtain the data and again if you do it how
I stated through the web interface or you want to do it programmatically either way is your call
but
Then you can go into the specific methods. So all of these
Modules are set up in a similar fashion. So you have your method section
It kind of goes through what the script is what script is available
What you're doing why you're doing it and then
at the end of the method section
and you'll go into your results.
And I guess also just to clarify,
you have your parameters where you can adjust
so that you can modify the pipeline
and interpret the different results as well.
So then here's some results.
When you run the pipeline, you should be able to match up.
And then you're gonna be able to generate a UMAP
to be able to look at the different cell type annotation
based on your different donors.
So this is donor wand, just as an example.
And then it goes into an interpretation section,
as well as in extending the analysis.
Like I was mentioning before, here's
some different things to consider if you
wanted to go beyond the course that I have put forward.
And then I leave some open questions
just to get you to think and consider what
what is the point of what we're doing and what are some different exploratory considerations
that you can also follow. Then the appendix A will have all associated supporting documentation.
This will include if you wanted to source everything programmatically, it will give
you the actual code that you can execute directly from your terminal and different parameters
as well and then it ends with the references.
So now to transition to the actual notebook file,
so for module one, again, this aligns well with the PDF.
And you'll be able to go through and you'll just
be able to set up, interpret what is being done,
and run end to end without any sort of problems.
Of course, when the data is actually secured
on your local device.
So how the directory is set up is that you have the primary Jupiter notebook
that gives a little bit of markdown context to each section.
And then you have supported scripts for each notebook that you can look at the
different Python helper functions, etc. that I integrated into this overall training.
So this is module one and
Now we will transition to module two.